A Guide to the Barbara T Spann Manuscript Collection on “Carlby”, 1966-1977
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Barbara T Spann Manuscript Collection on “Carlby”, 1966-1977
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 08-10
1.5 linear feet
The Barbara T Spann Manuscript Collection on “Carlby” consists of 1.5 linear feet and spans the years 1966-1977. The collection contains correspondence; photocopies of newspaper clippings; illustrations; photocopies and tracings of maps from 1833 to 1973; family trees for the Washington and Booth families; handwritten research notes and reference cards; and several rough and preliminary drafts of Carlby.
Spann, Barbara Towner (1929-2001)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Unknown. Collection presumably donated by the Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning
Historical and Biographical Information
Barbara Towner Spann was born on October 31, 1929. She earned a Bachelor of Arts degree in American History, Philosophy, and Religion in 1951 and a Master of Religious Education in 1952 from Southern Methodist University. She worked for the Smithsonian Press, retiring in 1992 as Managing Editor of the Series Section. Spann died on July 11, 2001 of pneumonia at her home in Henrico County, Virginia.
In February 1973, Fairfax County contracted Spann to undertake a study of the historic house, “Carlby”. She was responsible for documenting and presenting the historical significance of the house for inclusion on the Fairfax County Historical Landmarks Survey, later known as the Fairfax County Inventory of Historic Sites. Carlby is a Georgian style house built in the mid-eighteenth century by George Booth (1679-1763?) in Sussex County, Virginia. In 1946, Captain Carl Washburn Porter and his wife Beatrice McKnight Porter purchased the house, known at the time as the “Old Mitchell House,” and had it moved to a property along Dogue Creek in Fairfax County, Virginia that was originally part of George Washington’s Mount Vernon estate. As of 2018, the house still stands at 4509 Carlby Lane in Alexandria, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Barbara T Spann Manuscript Collection on “Carlby” consists of 1.5 linear feet and spans the years 1966-1977. The collection contains correspondence; photocopies of newspaper clippings; illustrations; photocopies and tracings of maps from 1833 to 1973; family trees for the Washington and Booth families; handwritten research notes and reference cards; and several rough and preliminary drafts of Carlby. Subjects covered are Carlby and historic buildings of Fairfax County.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Plans for Carlby, Alexandria, Va. [microform] MICR V 975.529 P 1974, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
None
Index Terms
Carlby, Va.; Historic Buildings - Virginia - Fairfax County; Porter, Beatrice McKnight (1898-1984); Porter, Carl Washburn (1896-1989); Spann, Barbara Towner (1929-2001)
Container List
- Barbara Towner Spann Resume, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence (Part 1 of 2), 1966-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence (Part 2 of 2), 1966-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Illustrations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Maps (photocopies and tracings), Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Washington Family Genealogy and Booth Family Genealogy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Research Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Research Materials and Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Rough Draft, Handwritten by Chapter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Rough Draft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Preliminary Draft, 1975 February 13 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Rough Draft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Rough Draft (carbon copy), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Rough Draft, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Rough Draft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Rough Draft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Research and Reference Note Cards, Undated (Box 3, Folder -)